Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting New Haven, Connecticut
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Oral histories documenting New Haven, Connecticut
2003-2007
RU 1055
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
97101
The materials consist of audio recordings and transcripts of oral histories conducted by New Haven Oral History Project staff with New Haven, Connecticut, citizens.
Original digital audio recordings were created by a number of different interviewers. The original audio produced varied in size, file format, and file naming conventions. Many recordings were split into multiple parts by the original digital recording devices (logical files). Processed master files were created by merging the separate parts and normalizing into standard file formats. In some cases, naming conventions of the originals may have resulted in processed masters and use copies that were created in the incorrect order. When available, refer to the transcript for guidance in determing order of the recordings. Transcripts refer to the original audio files when providing contextual notes (e.g. [END TAPE 1]).
New Haven Oral History Project (New Haven, Conn.)
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 14-B (YRG 14-B), Records of academic departments and programs of the Yale Faculty of Arts and Sciences.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were a gift of Andrew Horowitz, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
The records are arranged alphabetically by last name of interviewee.
Biographical / Historical
The New Haven Oral History Project (NHOHP) was founded in September, 2003 by Andrew Horowitz and Glenda Gilmore as a special project of the Yale University History Department. Support for the NHOHP comes from the Yale University President's Office, the Yale University Library Department of Manuscripts and Archives, and Yale's History and Political Science Departments. Past supporters have included the Yale College Dean's Office and the Community Foundation for Greater New Haven.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of audio recordings and transcripts of oral histories conducted by New Haven Oral History Project staff with New Haven, Connecticut, citizens.
New Haven (Conn.); New Haven (Conn.) -- History; Oral histories (document genres); Transcripts; Horowitz, Andy (Andrew Deutsch); New Haven Oral History Project (New Haven, Conn.)
- Interviews, Accession 2008-A-001
  - Abbatiello, Richard, 2004 July 15; computer file (WAV)
    Scope and Contents
    Richard Abbatiello recalls how urban renewal affected his life as a child growing up in New Haven. He was born on Chestnut Street in the East Street neighborhood, living above his father's machine shop, which his father started after leaving the A.C. Gilbert factory. Urban renewal forced the business to move to North Haven, and the family to move to Fair Haven Heights. Abbatiello discusses how the move affected him and the differences between the two neighborhoods, and reflects on his friend groups, working as a teenager in the family business, ethnic diversity, the roll of the Farnham Neighborhood House, and the merits of urban renewal. He also talks about his childhood admiration for Yale athletes like Johnny Lee and Albie Booth, and how that shaped his perception of the University.
    Interviewer: London, Douglas
    Length (min): 57
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
      General note
      Contact Public Services (phone: 203 432-1735, e-mail: mssa.reference@yale.edu) for information on accessing this digital object.
  - Abdussabur, Shafiq, 2007 April 5; computer file (WAV)
    Shafiq Abdussabur grew up in the Dixwell neighborhood in New Haven in the 1970s. Abdussabur recalls that Dixwell was not unified neighborhood. Although the street was almost entirely African-American, lines of geography and class were readily apparent to most residents. He suggests that there were effectively five distinct neighborhoods on Dixwell, and that class and geographical snobbery ran rampant among Dixwell residents, particularly the children with whom Abdussabur grew up. There was a key difference, he recalls, between people who were "poor" -- single parent families, living in the Elm Haven projects, on welfare -- and those who were just "broke." Abdussabur's family fell into the latter class. Despite these class divisions, he recalls that community life in the Dixwell area was vibrant, with lots of opportunity for kids and many positive Africa-American role models. It was, he says, "really a black-empowered zone from Dixwell all the way up." Abdussabur now works for the New Haven Police Department.
    Interviewer: Joseph, Amber
    - Use copy (part 1), compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 2Ua)
    - Use copy (part 2), compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 2Ub)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Acquavita, Fred, 2003 June 25; computer file (WAV)
    Fred Acquavita started teaching in the New Haven Public Schools in 1968, part of a crop of young, radical teachers to enter the New Haven schools at that time. He discusses his radicalization as a teacher and member of the teachers' union, the New Haven Federation of Teachers, in which he served in leadership positions. He describes his conflicts with the Board of Education and "conservative" teachers, describes his attempts at progressive teaching in various schools across the city, and offers his perspectives on education and unionization.
    Interviewer: Strohl, Nicholas
    Length (min): 80, 5
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Alderman, Norman, 2005 February 12; computer file (WAV)
    Norman Alderman is the third-generation owner of Alderman-Dow Iron and Metal Company, the oldest scrap metal business in New Haven, founded in 1895. Alderman discusses the nature of the scrap metal business, and Jewish and family businesses in general. He offers his views on business development in New Haven in the second half of the twentieth century. Alderman-Dow had to move from its original location on Dow Street in the Oak Street neighborhood because of urban renewal.
    Interviewer: Brogadir, Benjamin
    Length (min): 46
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Argento, Theresa, 2004 March 9; computer file (WAV)
    Theresa Argento recalls life before and during urban renewal in Wooster Square. One of seven children born to Italian immigrant Nadio Carrano, Argento offers memories of the neighborhood and family life pre-redevelopment -- comparisons to life in Amalfi, the role of the Sargent Hardware Company in the neighborhood, trips to Lighthouse Point, Lucibello's Pastry Shop, and to New York City to see Frank Sinatra sing. Her family owned Carrano's produce market on Chapel Street, which was demolished in the course of construction of interstate 91. Argento describes being evicted from the family's home above the store, and moving with her mother to the Annex section of New Haven. She also describes how redevelopment affected the St. Andrews Society, an Italian fraternal organization, and St. Michael's Church. Argento often gathers with other former neighborhood residents to reminisce about the old neighborhood at events like the Saint Andrews Feast and the Wooster Square Cherry Blossom Festival.
    Interviewer: Barca, Sarah
    Length (min): 65
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Barbieri, Norma (with Theresa Argento), 2005 February 24
    Norma Barbieri, the daughter of Italian immigrants, grew up in the Wooster Square neighborhood. She describes her father's decision to immigrate and his enduring love for the Italian language. Barbieri spoke Italian at home, but recalls being forced to speak English in school. She tells how as a child she played with being bilingual, laughing at her mother as she read the comics aloud in broken English, or how Barbieri gave nicknames to all the neighborhood characters.Theresa Argento, sitting in on the interview, offers her own related reminiscences, and Barbieri and Argento together describe their efforts to have Italian taught in local schools, and recall stories about growing up in Wooster Square, and how the neighborhood changed over the course of their lives, particularly after urban renewal.
    Length (min): 73
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Bargar, Marvin, 2005 April 21; computer file (WAV)
    Marvin Bargar grew up in New Haven's Legion Avenue neighborhood, graduated from Hillhouse High School in 1943, then returned to New Haven in 1950 after serving in the Army and graduating from the University of Connecticut. He discusses growing up in New Haven's Jewish community, the changes to the Legion Avenue neighborhood in the 1950s and 1960s, and his current efforts to preserve the city's Jewish history. Bargar first recalls his childhood in the Legion Avenue area. Most of the families in the area were Jewish or Italian American and lived in two- or three-family homes. He then proceeds to talk about the changing face of the neighborhood after World War II and suburban flight. As families became more affluent, they purchased cars and moved to single-family homes in the suburbs. Bargar, his wife, and children moved to Westville in the late 1950s but, dissatisfied with the schools, they moved to Hamden in 1968. Bargar laments Richard Lee's redevelopment projects because he believes that they destroyed Jewish community and businesses in the Legion Avenue and Oak Street areas. Bargar also discusses his work with the Jewish Historical Society, part of Southern Connecticut University's Ethnic Heritage Center, and his interest in repairing and restoring the Orchard Street Synagogue.
    Interviewer: Miner, Casey
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Barnett, John, computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Green, Nicole
  - Barnston, Betsy, 2004 November 15; computer file (WAV)
    Betsy Barnston was born in the East Rock neighborhood to a German-Jewish family, descendents of what she describes as the original 1853 Jewish immigrant to New Haven. She describes the balance her family attempted to strike between remaining Jewish and assimilating to Christian culture. She talks about not being able to join the New Haven Lawn Club, and tensions between the Jews from Germany, who came to New Haven in the 19th century, and those from Eastern Europe who came later and tended, in her estimation, to be less assimilated and more religiously observant. Barnston describes her experiences at a Jewish summer camp, and also her family's move to Hamden in the context of other families she knew moving to the suburbs. The interview focuses around Barston's synagogue, Mishkan Israel, which moved from Audubon Street in New Haven to Hamden. Barnston also talks admiringly about Mishkan Israel's Rabbi Robert Goldburg, who was active in the civil rights movement and invited Stokely Carmichael to speak at the temple, and mentions her own involvement in the inter-racial organization The Group.
    Interviewer: Cohen-Wade, Aryeh
    Length (min): 60
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Berdon, Robert, 2006 February 17; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Witt, Carolyn and Nicole Green
  - Berke-Schlessel, Merle, 2005 March 14; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Ludwig, Maren
    Length (min): 33
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Bethea, Doug, 2007 February 22; computer file (WAV)
    Doug Bethea grew up in the Dixwell neighborhood. After graduating from high school, he decided to give something back the community, and organized the National Drill Team and Drum Squad, a drill team designed to give New Haven young adults an opportunity to see the world and a reason to stay off the streets. Although Bethea guesses that he has helped 2000 local kids over the years, he says that he is "very disappointed with the way the city is now, with the way that the area is now." Bethea compares the Dixwell neighborhood he sees and lives in today -- gun crime, drugs, no control or respect -- with the community he remembers from his childhood. Bethea discusses the sense of family and community that suffused that area during his childhood, and mourns the loss of this feeling. Attempts to improve life in the community by legislative or political means are doomed to failure, Bethea suggests, until residents of Dixwell rediscover the meaning of family and community. He also discusses the loss of his son to gun violence.
    - Use copy, compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 12U)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Bialecki, Anthony, 2005 November 22; computer file (WAV)
    Anthony Bialecki was a student at the un-school of New Haven in the late 1960s and early 1970s. Born in 1953, Bialecki grew up in Fair Haven but his family moved to North Haven when he began high school. A self-described member of the counterculture, Bialecki dropped out of high school during his sophomore year and, against his father's wishes, began to attend the un-school of New Haven, a small alternative school with commitments to political activism and community involvement. Bialecki discusses his time in high school and his interest in antiwar and civil rights activism. Much of the interview focuses on the Black Panthers and Bialecki's impressions of them as a white activist. He considers their relation to women, to older generations of African American activists, and to white political groups. He also talks about the Women's movement, the Weathermen, the American Independent Movement, and Students for a Democratic Society (SDS). Bialecki recounts the May 1, 1970 May Day demonstrations, which occurred when he was a student at the un-school. He describes the events that day, the speakers who attended, the response of the university, and the significance of the protests, especially in light of more violent contemporary events such as Kent State. Bialecki touches on his experiences in the Local 35 union at Yale, Yale's politics at the time, and the relationship between Yale students and local activist groups. He also compares youth political activism today to that of the 1960s.
    Interviewer: Bialecki, Jessica
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Bissell, Bret, 2005 February 6; computer file (WAV)
    Bret Bissell moved to New Haven in the mid-1960s as an intern for the National Assocation of Intergroup Relations. He eventually became executive director of the Human Relations Council in New Haven. After this group folded, Bissell, a self-described "social engineer," worked for a number of federally funded agencies, dealing at various points with integration, community planning, and housing. He discusses New Haven's years as a "model city," when the city served as the test subject for dozens of state and federal programs. Bissell calls New Haven's redevelopment project "well-managed," but he recognizes that it tore communities apart and encouraged white flight to the suburbs. Given his work, Bissell had an opportunity to view first-hand the relocation of New Haven families during redevelopment, and he spends a great deal of time discussing the effects of these relocation on the city, on its neighborhoods, and on public housing. He also discusses his family history, which includes a Civil Rights activist mother and a brother in the Weather Underground.
    Interviewer: Johnson, Emily
    Length (min): 76, 26
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Bissell, Patricia, 2007 April 11; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Ray, Ellen
  - Blaisdell, Virginia, 2005 November 16; computer file (WAV)
    Virginia Blaisdell moved to New Haven in 1962 after graduating from Wellesley College and became involved in the American Independent Movement. Blaisdell left that group in the early 1970s as she became involved in feminist politics. Her interview focuses on her experiences as a feminist and her relationships with other political activist groups. Blaisdell discusses her impressions of the American Independent Movement and the Black Panthers, both of which she felt were too male-dominated. She also talks about the whiteness of the women's movement and the tensions between African American rights groups and women's rights groups. In the 1970s, Blaisdell participated in a womens' liberation rock band, helped organize New Women's and Our Bodies courses, and helped women access abortions. Her interview also discusses her contentious relationships with the New Haven Police Department and Yale University. Blaisdell was one of forty women who successfully sued the city of New Haven for illegal wiretapping activities. Blaisdell currently works for the unions at Yale, and talks about her belief in the university's tendency to be conservative and resistant to reforms. Blaisdell also talks about her experience as a photographer and her work for the New Haven Advocate.
    Interviewer: Nole, Nicole
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Bontatibus, John, 2007 February 10; computer file (WAV)
    John Bontatibus was born in Clinton Avenue in the Chatham Square section of Fair Haven in 1932, which was then known as "Clam Town." Bontatibus remembers working on his father's milk farm in Branford, and making deliveries around the New Haven area. Bontatibus dwells on the variety of childhood activities available around Fair Haven: street games after school, playing in Indian Cave in Fair Haven Heights, ice skating in Hollywood Park, being in the Boy Scouts, going to Savin Rock in West Haven, dances at the Atwater Training School. He also recalls how the combination of Dutch Elm Disease and the Great 1938 Hurricane destroyed most of New Haven's Elm trees. He talks about the neighborhood's ups and downs since the 1980s, focusing on differences between renters and homeowners, and talks about the work of the Chatham Square Neighborhood Association. He also discusses his view of how race relations have evolved over the years.
    Interviewer: Woerner, Austin
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Bovilsky, Deborah, 2005 February 5; computer file (WAV)
    Deborah Bovilsky was raised in Kentucky, and attended Northwestern University before moving to New Haven in mid 1960s. Her husband, Jay, attended Yale Law School while Deborah studied psychology at Columbia University. She lived for a number of years in downtown New Haven, and was active in leftist causes during the 1960s. She discusses her impressions of the Bobby Seale/Black Panther trial and New Haven's redevelopment plans. She also discusses a number of unique community programs that grew up in New Haven in the mid-60s, including High School in the Community, Cloud 9 (a center for runaway children), and a cooperative teaching center run by First and Summerfield Church. Bovilsky was an active member of the Mishkan Israel synagogue, led Rabbi Robert Goldberg. Mishkan Israel was an activist temple, involved in the anti-Vietnam movement and Civil Rights in New Haven as well as in the Deep South. Bovilsky later moved to the Beaver Hill section of New Haven, near Southern Connecticut State University. She discusses raising children in a racially integrated section of the city.
    Length (min): 55
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Brandenberg, Arthur, 2004 October 29; computer file (WAV)
    Arthur Brandenberg came to Yale in 1961 to serve as chaplain to Methodist students and took part in antiwar and civil rights activism on campus until he left in 1971. On the verge of being fired from Duke University for his liberal racial views, Brandenberg accepted an invitation from William Sloan Coffin, Jr., the University Chaplain, to come to Yale. Brandenberg discusses the religious community at Yale in the 1960s and the community and national activism of the campus ministries. Brandenberg took an active part in the Yale Religious Ministry, a coalition of Protestant, Jewish, and Catholic groups at Yale that became involved in social politics in the 1960s. Brandenberg remembers the student organizing initiatives by undergraduates Peter Countrymen and Joseph Lieberman and law student Maryanne Wright. He also tells the story of his arrest in St. Augustine Florida, where he and several other members of the Yale Religious Ministry were jailed after a civil rights protest. He talks at great length about Coffin and about Yale President Kingman Brewster and praises their liberal views on civil rights and their activism. Brandenberg also discusses his perception of the Black Panthers, an organization that he believed was too militant.
    Length (min): 58
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Brodhead, Richard, 2003 November 3; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Plischke, Moritz
    Length (min): 18
  - Brown, Lillian, 2004 March 4; computer file (WAV)
    Lillian Brown discusses life in the African-American community located in the Newhallville and Dixwell neighborhoods of New Haven. Brown moved into her home in Newhallville in 1953, and remained for the next five decades. She raised six children, and worked at the Winchester rifle factory. She discusses the changes wrought by urban renewal in the 1950s and 1960s, changes that she feels were not for the best. Brown feels particular ire for the adminsitration of mayor Richard Lee, whose urban renewal projects, she feels, disregarded the needs of the black community and left huge holes in the Newhallville landscape. Brown's opposition to urban renewal led her to become more active in city politics, culminating in her election as City Treasurer in early 1970s. She discusses the strategies used by black politicians and civic leaders to better the lives of their constituents in the face of a frequently hostile city government. Brown comments on the long-term changes in the landscape and community of Newhallville, including the construction of housing projects and the disappearance of small businesses.
    Interviewer: Ortiz, Claudia
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Bruskin, Sydney, 2003 November 13; computer file (WAV)
    Sydney Bruskin was born in Ansonia, CT, moved to New Haven as child, and remained in the city for most of his life. The child of immigrant Jewish parents, Sydney completed elementary school in New Haven before enrolling at Hillhouse High School. Bruskin describes the life of a high school student in New Haven in the 1930s, focusing on his friends (mostly the children of Jewish immigrants), classes, and ex-curricular activies. After graduating from Hillhouse, he attended Yale, but, due to the depression, was forced to live at home and commute to school. He discusses the difficulties caused by these circumstances, as well as the anti-semitism faced at Yale. Bruskin Majored in French, but had trouble finding a teaching job during the Depression. After borrowing a bit of money from his father, Bruskin opened a bicycle rental and repair shop on Chapel Street.
    Interviewer: Rubin, Tamar
    Length (min): 44
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Calabresi, Guido, 2006 March 30; computer file (WAV)